hello and welcome everyone it's November
20th 2023 we're here in actm orst stream
5.1 with anamarie Swan discussing
ecological organizations so thank you
very much for joining we will be looking
forward to a talk followed by a
discussion so to those who are watching
along live please feel free to add your
questions in the live chat and thank you
again for joining Anam marray really
looking forward to this oh pleasure
thank you so much for having me um it's
been very interesting to discover the
work that you're doing here at the
Institute I'd never heard of the the
work of active interference the phrase
like what's that about and it struck me
as I was um as you were explaining it to
me a little bit when you reached out and
as I
um explored the term myself that it's
it's fascinating because it feels like
we're coming into organizations or C
Dynamics perhaps from different
entryways but I can really see the the
small amount I know the relationship um
ways that we could explore together so
it's a real pleasure to be here and talk
to you a bit about ecological
organizations um yeah actually I think
you've introduced you you shared the
link to my site in your in the in the so
I won't dive too much into kind of
introducing myself but yeah I'm based
here in the UK in
exer um and um I've been absolutely
fascinated with organizations and group
dynamics um very specifically for about
seven years and that's become my work in
my world um and over those years
my my perception of organizations and
and groups within organizations has
changed quite a bit and where I'm at now
is is looking at um organizations
through this very specific lens of of
ecological
organizations so let me um get set up
and then we'll dive into the course into
the
talk hey
so during today's talk I'm asking you to
join me on a journey into exploring and
examining the nature of an organization
as a co-created story and why this story
matters in particular to how we view the
role of
organizations we'll set off on our
journey by investigating the story of
our body as a
singularity a complete and separate
entity with clear and discoverable
borders take what we learn about our
bodies into investigating the story of
an
organization as a singularity a complete
and separate entity with clear and
discoverable
borders and with these investigations as
our signposts we'll arrive at ecological
organizations as a co-creative story
that asks us to radically reimagine the
role of organizations in the
world as with all good stories that we
Center the that Center a journey we'll
need some aids to help us along the way
so first we'll hold truth as a lowercase
te truth that is formed of living
questions that open up new
questions second we'll adopt different
lenses to look at an organization
through including an animist lens and
third will hold the we that I speak of
as a we that's whiteness dominated
European centered and a neoc capitalist
world that I inhabit and not as a
reflection of all people and all
perspectives I truly believe that the
time has come for us to reimagine
stories of organizations as ecological
and through co-creating the story of
ecological organizations become
radically responsive and responsible
ecosystem
stewards to give ourselves some way of
tasting ing what being ecological means
I'm going to ask you to close your eyes
for a while you don't have to but I
think you'll find this talk much richer
if you join me by investigating your
lived
experience bring your attention to your
body what is your experience of being in
your body right
now what physical Sensations do you
notice do you notice your heart beating
can you feel your body breathing in and
out now bring your attention to what
you're sitting or standing
on investigate the place where your body
meets another
surface can you tell where that point of
contact exactly
is are you losing heat or feeling a
difference in temperature at the place
that your body meets another material
now widen your attention to to your
external
environment what sounds can you
hear what Sensations are you
experiencing that arise from your
environment can you notice dampness heat
Stillness or movement in the
air now we'll do some time travel
so go back to the start of your day and
travel through
it perhaps you woke up in bed next to
someone and you you were aware of that
other body near
you or perhaps you alone and you were
aware of that sense of your being alone
in your
bed recall the contact of the sheets on
your
skin later on in the day you likely
interacted with substances like
toothpaste to brush your teeth water to
wash your face perhaps you filled a
kettle with water and then press the on
button then drank a hot
drink have you eaten
today if you have remember that process
of eating the food first outside your
body then in your mouth then
swallowed how about bringing other
people into your day have you been in
the same space as someone else
today did you sit next to them walk past
them on the street perhaps make direct
physical contact with another human
being at the very least you're all here
on this Zoom with me so we're in some
way in connection and you've likely
sitting at a computer or on a mobile
phone which means you've turned on a
screen and your fingertips have hit
computer keys or interacted with a
mobile phone
screen through all of this from the
moment you woke up to right now did you
feel like a singularity a complete and
separate entity with clear and
discoverable
borders keeping your eyes chut we're
going to investigate your days
experiences again add into all of those
activities the estimated 39 trillion
bacteria in or on the human
body now we only have 300 Al in human
cells in our body so we have more
bacteria than human
cells we have bacteria in our gut on our
eyelashes our skin up our nose our belly
buttons we have it in our lungs we have
it in our genitals and we have it in our
bladders we house multiple microbiomes
in and on our
body perhaps after all you weren't just
a singularity a complete and separate
entity with clear and discoverable
borders going about your day but a
creature that is more of a
multitude can you locate the very
borders of
you where exactly is the edge of you and
the start of something
else is your border your skin and
everything your body holds within
it what about your hair is each strand
of the hair on your head your arm arms
your legs your genitals your eyelashes
are part of
you well how much hair do you think you
shed today it's likely you wouldn't
notice all of it a hair from our head
holds a viable DNA if kept
stable is that hair no longer part of
you the moment it's no longer on your
body if that strand of head hair
contains your
DNA what about skin cells are they a
part of
you how many skin cells were you
shedding when you were in bed as you
brushed your teeth as you ate or as
you're right now when is this your skin
a part of you and when is it
not your Consciousness your emotions
your awareness of you can you pinpoint
the edges of these are they contained
within the edges of your skin or do they
travel outside where do you really begin
and
end think about the last time that you
held someone's hand could you tell at
all times where the edges of you ended
and the edges of the other person
began our Reliance on our environment is
a matter of life and death we eat food
and converted to energy because
otherwise we'd starve we drink water and
are hydrated because otherwise we die of
thirst we breathe in air and utilize the
chemicals within because otherwise we'd
suffocate as we process and expel what
we consume as you've consumed today
aided by chemical proess in the body
where are the lines between food water
air being separate from us and when
they're a part of
us when we breathe we move carbon
through our blood into our lungs and
expel it at what exact moment in the
conversion process is the carbon part of
you and when is it no longer you perhaps
after all you weren't just a singularity
a complete and separate entity with
clear and discoverable borders going
about your day but a creature that is
very much of your
environment now still with your eyes
shut bring all of these multitudes this
environmental Reliance interactions into
your awareness of yourself as a being
that has multiple
relationships multiple
interactions the relationships and
interactions with loved ones friends
colleagues people at the supermarket on
the train or on the bus and walking past
you in the
park think about how you're carrying
those relationships and interactions
with you every day with family close
friends Partners we're carrying years
sometimes Decades of relationships and
interactions with us as we go about our
day now extend those relationships and
interactions to include everything else
you meet and interact with and are
affected
by objects animals trees Rivers plants
clouds Sunshine electricity the internet
computer software and on and on and
on where exactly do you begin and end
where are the edges of you the human
being perhaps after all you aren't just
a singularity a complete and separate
entity with clear and discoverable
borders going about your day but a
creature that is a multitude a multitude
of your environment deeply and
irrevocably amhed into constellations of
relationships and
interactions constantly being rearranged
and
rearranging impossible to point to where
we end and others and other things
really
begin now now extend that awareness of
this magnitude for ourselves and include
every other zoombe other other human
being with us right now or watching this
zo at some point each of us with
trillions of bacteria shedding hair and
skin breathing eating drinking moving
through our day carrying multiple
relationships and
interactions this is what it seems to me
it is to be human you are you I am I we
can clearly point to where you end and I
begin and yet when we really explore it
when we close our eyes we find that the
human body is actually dispersed a
multitude that's more bacteria than
human cells a constant shedding and
regrowth our cells our very selves being
arranged by our environment and
rearranging it
constantly when we close our eyes eyes
we can experience both the borders and
the borderlessness of being a human
being and we can ask the question do we
really know where things end and
everything else
begins so when you're ready to step back
into your Singularity at least for a
while feel free to open your
eyes if your experience just then was
anything like mine when I shut my eyes
and bring my attention to my body and
then extend it outwards what you've just
experienced is how I directly experience
what it means to be ecological to be a
living organism in relationship with
their
environment more than that we know that
there are ecological relationships being
lived within and on us the relationship
between us and our gut microbiome is
just one kind of ecological relationship
with our gut and us it's a mutualistic
symbiotic relationship meaning that
different species live in Closs in close
proximity and both the species
benefit ecological relationships are
intimate and meaningful
relationships in the case of us and our
G bacteria we host the bacteria for
their lifetime we give them what they
need to thrive and they help us digest
our food access nutrients develop and
maintain our immun system and protect us
against harmful
Invaders healthy and happy gut
microbiome equals healthier and happier
human
bodies I know this well one of the
challenging health issues I have means
some of my gut bacteria that I rely on
for health and well-being has migrated
from the large intestine into the small
causing all sorts of Havoc to my small
intestin and causing me daily issues for
my immune system access to nutrients and
food dig
digestion now I'm not a biologist and
this is not a biology lesson but when I
was thinking about how to best convey
what it is that led me to birth the
ecological organiz ecological
organization's framework and the story
of ecological organization at rest on I
realized that it's through my awareness
of myself as an ecological being hosting
and being hosted by ecological
relationships that was the path into
seeing and experiencing organizations as
ecological and I realized without
touching the experience of being
ecological then ecological organizations
just become a lifeless Theory and
nothing ecological is
lifeless now that we've lived our
experience of being both bordered and
borderless we can investigate ecological
organizations starting by looking for
where an organizations border lies
it seems to me that we have co-created a
story of organizations as singularities
as complete and separate entities with
clear and discoverable
borders and I believe that believing
this co-created story to be a fact to be
truth with a capital T can do immense
damage to an organization an
organization's members and the
ecosystems and social systems that
organization is situated
within and most of us here could
probably give a definition of what an
organization is we might explain it as a
group of people with a shared purpose or
goal with a specific legal legal
status we might include to that
description that it has employees or
members we might also add that it often
has a head office or multiple offices
released an address that we can write to
all all seems pretty
obvious but when searching for the
borders the edges of an organization I
found that these descriptions leave me
unable to actually pinpoint
them so let's start with an organization
as a a group of people that have a
shared purpose or goal that makes a lot
of sense to me but when I look to find
the organization here I end up
frustrated well people share around
people group around all sorts of shared
purposes and goals that doesn't bring us
to the organization
itself for starters we're grouping here
today with a shared purpose but we're
not an
organization people group up in parks
for yoga classes or group walks they're
not
organizations if I want to find the
borders of an organization if it is a
group of people with a shared PSAL goal
I want to know where I can find the
edges
when the members of this group go home
at the end of The Working Day if they're
in an office or an allocated building or
when they stop working on organizational
tasks if they work from home does the
organization cease to exist for a
while what about at weekends when an
organization's members are with their
families or hiking Mountain Trails or
flying to a new city or watching
TV has the organization itself become
somehow dissolved at these times
what about when a member leaves and
another arrives what if all the original
members of a group leaves an
organization and it's formed of entirely
new members does it as an organization
change the atmosphere might the
direction might maybe they'll even
Rebrand but does the thing
change even if an organization merges
with another organization if we look to
find the borders of the or organization
as a group of people that are different
to everyone else we know that people
aren't singularities they're not
complete and separate entities with
clear and Def discoverable borders
themselves so that we know that a group
of people isn't ever just a group of
people it's a group of human beings that
are deeply iMed in their environment and
that carry with them into their working
lives a multitude of living relationship
ships and daily
interactions I then find myself
investigating the physical can we locate
an organization in an office a building
in a home office when I look there for
an organization I find walls floors
ceilings lights desks electricity
internet and so
on I can locate those things but I'm not
finding the organization
there any of those elements can be
replaced and an organization stays the
same where for example is the physical
divide of an organization in the shared
floor or building when do I know when
I'm standing in an organization or
outside of it poost might get delivered
visitors in an office come and
go and yet does part of the organization
go with those visitors what happens when
an organization expands into two offices
has it been split in half many of us are
or many of us are members of
organizations that don't even have an
office I've been a COR member of a
number of organizations where I've never
met the other members in person and
where we all work from different
locations around the
world so then I looked to legal
status most organizations have one an
organization is most often a nonprofit a
limited company a church a school an
institution um such as yourselves a
purpose-led
Enterprise still I can't find its
borders the organization isn't the
computer file or the piece of paper that
says an organization exists and affords
it as certain legal
status I find that when I investigate an
organization in this way I feel almost a
little embarrassed that these
investigations feel a little childish we
know that an organization isn't actually
a thing none of us try and touch one and
we know in a way it's as much of an idea
as anything else we could say it's an
idea a story of all the above elements
combined the members where they work the
shared purpose or goal the legal status
they have but I keep getting stuck when
I think of the human body and how easy
it is to say that yes look they're at
that body that's a singularity a
complete and separate entity with clear
and discoverable borders until I
investigate it and find it to be both
bordered and borderless that to be human
is to be ecological and be IM mesed
within ecological
relationships even if we land or agree
at organizations's being an idea that we
all agree to share that I could never
touch or find its edges in the same way
that I could touch you and say look
there you are we still know that
organizations exist the impact of our
the impact of them on our lives is
beyond doubt and Beyond
argument many of us are members of an
organization you are members of an
institution and at some point or we will
at some point be in our lifetime some
member of an
organization we might rely on them for
our income we have relationships and
interactions with member of the
organization and relationships and
interactions with members of other
organizations we look to organizations
to pay taxes to keep promises to sell us
things provide us with things take care
of
services the impact and output of them
is without argument we have daily lived
experiences of them here in the UK I am
daily experiencing the impact of actions
and outputs of large to small
organizations depending on them for my
heating my water my food my electricity
and so on at this particular time some
of the organizational impacts are so
impactful that they radically change my
daily life as a UK citizen for the
worse when I examine an organization
look to where its edges are just like
with our bodies I find that instead of
Singularity instead of a complete and
separate entity with clear and
discoverable borders there exists both
borders and
borderlessness take the organiz iation
Amazon as an example I know Amazon the
organization exists I and you could
point to an Amazon delivery centers the
delivery trucks they utilize their
customer service team we can buy
products in their
organization we could divide people into
Amazon employees or those working for
Amazon and those that aren't we could
even track the peripherals the supply
chains who does business with Amazon who
their stockholders
are it starts to get trickier though to
divide people into who is impacted by
the actions and output of Amazon and who
isn't it doesn't seem to me to be a huge
leap to Guess that we'd find that every
single human on this planet is in some
way affected by the actions and output
of
Amazon it gets even trickier to divide
the everything that is affected by the
actions and output of Amazon and those
that aren't like the impact on Earth's
natural ecosystems and all the life
forms that dwell within them and in
relationship with them it doesn't seem
to me to be a huge leap to Guess that
we'd find that everything on this planet
is in some way affected by the actions
and outputs of
Amazon but it's not just huge
organizations like Amazon that have
external actions and and outputs and
impacts investigate any organization and
it becomes challenging to separate out
the impact and actions from that
organization after all the shared idea
of say a group of people with a shared
purpose and goal they have a purpose and
a
goal we still need to Define an
organization though even if we find
there are no true borders we need to
know who works for an organization and
who doesn't which office to go to or who
to have an asent conversation with I
need to know as a member of an
organization who's paying me what tasks
I'm responsible for what purpose or goal
I'm contributing to contributing
to we need to know who to hold
accountable and who to ask questions of
my work especially is hugely inspired by
Commons and I'm very excited by
organizations as
Commons the first step in creating and
governing a Commons is to Define it to
Define its borders so that we can
understand who or what is within that
Commons and who and what is
without it's the same with humans we
need to know that you are you and I am I
besides each of us humans is unique and
that's wonderful as each organization is
unique to me when I investigate it the
nature of an organization seems as iMed
in relationships as made up of
relationships as a body is the edges
become hard to determine what's taking
place within its borders effects and is
affected by what's taking place outside
of its borders what's taking place
outside of its borders affects and is
affected by what's taking place within
its
borders if we didn't create stories of
definable borders an organization
wouldn't exist but we need to remember
that these borders like most borders are
a story that we co-create and keep
co-creating once we hold organizations
as both bordered and borderless as
having edges that are tricky to find we
can co-create a reimagined
organizational story that of ecological
organizations ecological organizations
are organizations that are curious about
themselves and how how they relate with
their
environments they're organizations that
recognize that within their so-called
borders they are a web of everchanging
fluid responsive
relationships from the relationships
between their members to the
relationships playing out and within
their systems and social norms and that
recognize that outside of their So-Cal
borders they are affecting and being
affected by webs of everchanging fluid
responsive relationships that are the
ecosystems and social systems and an
organization is situated
in ecological organizations are
organizations that recognize that they
are being constantly rearranged by
relationships and all that dwell within
those relationships and are constantly
rearranging relationships and all that
dwell within those
relationships because to be is to be in
and of a multitude of relationships as
it is with us
humans thinking back to that huge
multitudes of relationships interactions
and the intimate symbiotic relationships
that each of us human being carries and
meets and is AR rearranged by every
single day that you experience when you
shut your eyes bring that complexity
that interrelating into your
understanding of an organization even
the very
[Music]
smallest as well as the webs of
relationships that each human member of
an organization is woven into and brings
with them into an organization every
single time they set foot in that
virtual or real
office think about the multitude of
relationships that are involved every
time people work together in different
formations from pairs to Triads to small
teams large teams departments boards and
so on on on top of all that bring in
investors in all of their relationships
stakeholders in all of their
relationships clients or customers and
all of their
relationships now bringing the seeming
externalities the neighborhoods the
natural ecosystems the man-made
structures El such as electricity grids
and phone lines and
internet when we start to hold the
Myriad of ways that an organization
affects or impacts all the relationships
inside its imagined borders and all the
relationships outside its imagined
borders now we are touching the
ecological nature of
organizations through looking at an
organization through this lens we can
become curious about where and how an
organization is causing harm or being
helpful curious about where and how all
the different relationships within an
organization are hurting an or
organization's member or helping them or
likely both we can become curious about
how the relationships within an
organization are hurting the
organization or helping the organization
maybe
both curious about where and how the
actions and output of an organization
are hurting or helping those small
communities the large communities
neighborhoods nature social norms
natural systems man-made systems more
than human beings and the Very Earth
itself we can utilize this lens to trace
and observe and intentionally improve
the relationships that an organization
and its members are consistently
rearranged by and are constantly
rearranging both within the organization
and within the local Regional bi
Regional and Global ecosystems and
social systems an or that an
organization is located
within there's one thing that we still
have to
explore let's revisit and examine again
the two terms ecology and ecological
relationships the
ecology um the ecological is the
relationship between living organisms
and their
environments ecological relationships
are the relationship between living
organisms how then can an organization
be ecological be IM mesed within
ecological relationships if it is not a
living
organism well here's where another Lens
comes
in even if we understand that an
organization is a web of relationships
and interactions IM mesed in wider webs
of relationships and interactions if the
nature of an organization is a group of
people with a shared purpose or goal a
legal status members and so on on why
isn't every single group of people with
a shared purpose or goal and
organization when we whether we view
organizations as animate or inanimate is
it seems to me just another story that
we are co-creating together and over the
many years of my being fascinated with
organizational design strategy and
facilitation as well as group dynamics
playing out within
organizations I find myself relating to
organizations through an animist
lens where others just see organizations
as the elements the static elements the
grouping of business offices computers
decisions employees Partners production
output and legal status and so on I see
these as being the elements that birth
organizations into life as their own
beings breathed into Life by humans and
human
creativity beings that we can choose to
have the honor to nurture steward would
and hopefully one day support through a
good death this is the difference that I
find between groups gathering around a
share purpose or goal and an
organization so much opens up for me
when I view an organization as animate
instead of
inanimate now I as an organizational
member become an organizational Steward
listening deeply paying careful
attention to what the organization needs
and is telling me
being an organizational Steward becomes
one more way that I can honor life and
all the forms it takes one one more way
that I can choose to move toward right
relationship now I as an organizational
Steward become activated into radical
stewardship radical responsiveness and
responsibility for those relationships
within the co-created boundaries of an
organization and radical responsiveness
and responsibility of the relationships
within the multitudes of relationships
and organization is situated
within this then is the heart of what to
me an or ecological organization
encompasses this is the reimagined
organizational story that moves and
activates and excites me this is how I
step further into activism into right
relationship and into stewardship
whether or not you choose to adopt an
animous lens or not or co-create a story
of ecological organizations or not I
hope that this talk will at least ignite
some interesting breadcrumbs you might
want to follow and leave you with
questions to live into and to explore
thank you so much for your
attention thank you
awesome all
right
wow thank you very experiential and it's
really exciting to hear I think there's
a lot of touch points with what we talk
about at active inference and so there's
a lot of ways
to
explore anything else you want to add or
can I go into some questions let's go
into them let's dive
I really like this tension between the
singularity and the
multitude and that's something that
comes up in the ant colony in the slime
mold it's like nothing is
just uni components everything that we
call thing when we zoom
in it
becomes blurrier and it becomes more
multi-agent at a smaller
scale right
so H how do
we how do we scaffold then our role as
on one hand stewarding the little guys
inside and which
whose goals and histories we can't step
into their shoes
directly and
similarly for processes that are bigger
and slower than we
are so H H how do we jump I felt like I
was ready to jump
somewhere when my eyes were
closed yeah that's really interesting
firstly I love the because I think when
we talked before I think we did end up
talking about ants in some way or
certainly I I remember and I I think
that's such a great story
because
um to understand and like with
organizations we have to somehow find
some way to Def to make the definition
right in these these tensioned Borders
or borderlessness we have to understand
what we're studying and what we aren't
studying and so I I
guess one of the ways into it or
certainly I think one of the ways into
it for me of of that activation of that
jumping is through some def defining
it's I feel like that's really important
um um as long as we do that defining
with the awareness that we are creating
this story and the maybe understanding
for ourselves why we're creating that
definition so when I um in simile when I
feel that kind of excitement or that
sense of jumping I want to both nurture
and care for what's happening within an
organization I want to nurture and care
and support and Steward as much much as
I can for for the impact of it and all
the different relationships that are
happening at some point it can be it's
just too much really like they can if we
were to follow relationships in the same
way I'd imagine with ants if you were to
follow their relationships to the next
relationships and the next relationships
and the next relationships at some point
you reach a level where
um what do you focus on where do you
even start everything dissipates um the
attention dissipates it's it's all too
much
so I guess all I can come back to is to
a personal sense of how
I how I cope with that Liv tension
experience of being an organizational
member which is
that
where where am I drawn to what think I
can have the most impact on right now
what's the information that feels big
enough to ENC Compass some level of
impact and feel small enough to cope
with um if we go back to organizations
very specifically and let's I'm just
trying to think of an example all right
let's let's take as an example
um so I until recently I'm still partner
in a in a wonderful small organization
called Nesta that creates technology um
to support self-organization and um
fairly small organization um very
globally located and with a very
specific way that the purpose of that
organization is being enacted through
the creation of software that helps
support um that help support
self-organization
well I can hold both I think at the same
time I can hold the size of that
organization and the care and the
stewardship of of of the humans within
it right understanding like what is
their well-being right now true
well-being not the well-being that comes
with yoga classes but like how do they
are they feeling seen and heard are they
feeling that they get to follow what
moves them does it feel like a right fit
within this organization right now um is
the work they're doing and they're
getting supported all of those things um
like what are the things happening at
home for them right now that um maybe
massively impact them are they someone
like myself that has um chronic health
conditions you know all of these things
we can sort of Ripple out in a very
manageable way we can really hold and
address and we can start to sorry we can
hold and address us as members as as
human beings as important human beings
and then I can look at Nester and I can
start to examine the different systems
and structures that are taking place
within Nester as a small organization
that maybe describe it as different
Hollands or different cells we can look
at each one and we can start to kind of
address it and see where their
relationships are and what's being
affected by what um and then I can
spread my attention more externally like
um as we're creating these new products
or is we're improving our products or
evolving our products who does this
touch who are products touching so we
can start to interact with our clients
so and we can also we can go in that
direction at the same time we can start
to look at what what supplies us um you
know are we what kind of um systems do
we rely on for our software are they
decentralized or centralized like we can
start to spread our our awareness and
our intentionality outwards at a very
manageable
Pace we might start to make decisions
like well really matters to us where our
energy comes from as an organization it
matters um what's suppliers um we have a
relationship with so we want to start
understanding the the the what's
important to our suppliers but we also
want to start exploring what's important
to our clients um so we might start to
to really understand like what are the
pressures they're experiencing what are
the stresses they're experiencing what's
the impact they're having and through
this way in a way I guess what we're
doing is we're gently starting to to
practice because it is always just a
practice practice what it's like to
bring attention to both things at the
same time to start gently extending
awareness outside of the borders in
manageable ways um while at the same
time holding just as important and
understanding those effects how they
affect so might find that um you know
maybe a client having an incredible
challenging time um and we start to
support the clients in some way with
that in a different way and then
relationships change and we find new
Pathways internally within our own
environment if we're taking it to more
kind of not i' say so much extremes
that's not quite the right word but if
we're if we're looking to we're we're so
activated and that we have the ability
there are some really fascinating things
happening in the world there are um and
I forget the name but
um there are companies that are creating
um office buildings that are their own
ecosystems that are themselves living
ecosystems so they're bringing into
their immediate environment in through
those borders as they focus all of those
things they're actually bringing in um
externalities they're bringing those in
their they learning to live in a
different way so um I think if that kind
kind of answers your point I may have
gone off on a little tangent so if I do
I have a habit of doing that so let me
know at any times but I not all I can do
with say with that is I noticed for
myself
that there comes a point where vastness
and scales
become impossible to navigate they
become you know it's in the same way
with bodies like I can take care of my
body and I can help a certain amount of
people in my life in a direct and
intimate way but then my ability to have
a relationship with others gets less and
less and less
um yeah it's that kind
of touch on it
somewhat yeah like what I got in that
was when
we steal ourselves or steal ourselves
and and sit with that
fractal multitude it's like breathing
and then there's a point where it's like
I've breathed all I can breathe and then
we take the jump of faith and we do
something we take some action and that
might be an internal action like a shift
of attention it might be uh action on
our
border but by by being an action on our
border like our finger touching the
screen or doing some other action like
the the the Border itself becomes the
sight of action that right already is
beyond us but it's us but it's already
Beyond us yes I I like that very much
thank you I love how you put that what
come to mind when you were speaking was
um
how it seems to me more and more
important important that information
that we're Gathering from outside of us
becomes this close to real time data and
to immediate data as we can so that
we're when we're when we're in action on
those borders when we're activating
those borders and we're really kind of
interacting and keeping our attention on
those
interactions that we have as much as
possible of the best information coming
back to us what are the real effects we
having um what's the changes happening
in the world that we can hear as quickly
as possible to react to um a practical
kind of example of that
is
um in the way
that we often see organizations
triggering kind of sweeping changes um
let's say AI for an example I know
that's a whole ball of like stuff that
we might not want to open but but it's a
really for me one of the things that I
found incredibly troubling about AI is
how quickly AI has moved to a global
scale without really giving us as humans
and our systems and our environments and
I might be wrong an AI an AI person
might say no these have been done but
but it feels like we've we've moved to a
a global encompassing scale at an
overwhelming great um we haven't given
time to have more kind of
localized experiments that we can get as
true to realtime data about the impact
of AI on communities the impact of AI on
our work the impact of our AI on our
ecosystems impact on our Energy Systems
of running AI all of these things um
we've kind of got swept up and into this
enormity of it and you spoke earlier one
thing that really me as you talked about
you mentioned something I'm going to
forget the phrase but it made me think
of the different ways that we experience
time right you mentioned something I
think about how do we exist in this kind
of borderless bordered State and be in
touch with the externals when things may
be moving at different times deep time
or slow time or you said something do
you remember I don't no okay but it's
like we you know
sometimes AI makes me crave like whale
time it's like look at how slowly or
what does life look like for a wh it's
alive for like so long and it seems to
move in this particular way and then as
humans with something in AI we just move
often at these incredible speeds really
kind of removed from our
environments um and I find that very
disturbing like I physically find it
very distur steing at that idea and and
I look at kind of yeah this movement
with they eye and I get all the
organizations that are leading it and
and I kind of just want to ask them to
slow down it's like please just slow
down like it's not that
I reject I I don't think that we should
be evolving and changing and and um
innovating but but to really understand
to keep our intention on the borders of
ourselves our
organizations we have to also move at a
speed that allows us to bring in as real
as close to real time data as we can so
that we as organization members have the
best data the best
information and then we can start to
like really focus on as like how do we
as an
organization ensure that we have the
internal
relationships so healthy that we can
then respond internally as well to that
information as um not just as quickly as
we can but with as much
intentionality and absorbing it so that
really then that border becomes a place
of the the highest activity really in an
organization um it's where we meet the
outside world and you know we're
constantly going back there for as much
new information as we
can
awesome a lot to say on that I I love
the idea that where the rubber hits the
road or the ground floor is like the
coolest and actual place to be in a
decentralized organization I think
that's really cool I'm going to ask some
questions from the live chat great okay
Susan asks a lovely presentation how do
you explain the benefits of using this
lens to move to collective decision
[Music]
making well I don't know that I actually
do I I I don't think I I do in that
sense let let me explain so I come from
a background of collective decision
making I come from a a a Fascination in
in self-organizing and how groups
self-organize and make decisions but and
so I have an immense fascination with
that and of course how groups make
decisions is incredibly important how we
navigate our social norms how we
navigate being relational creatures um I
have a personal preference for things
like consent decision making um for
self-organization as a
base um
managing um approach because to to me it
affords so much that I see as
beneficial but I actually don't think in
my work of ecological organizations no
is that
true at the heart of it I guess what I'd
like people to come away with is
understanding that to view a an to view
an organization as ecological does not
put a preference on
something um
to understand something as
ecological is
is in the same way we look at if
studying the to ant we're understanding
something about the nature of an
organization itself that's what really
feels important to
me however I being an opinionated human
being have you know my strong opinions
and
um in the pH framework that I authored
as part of my kind of understanding of
my perspective and ecological
organizations being a self excuse me
being a self-organizing system and
understanding what that looks like for
people and also being relational a key
elements of the framework and the
framework really is just guidance it's
very much a personal perspective that
came from the work that I've done over
the years in self-organizing ation and
working with
organizations excuse me um that to me is
a lens that we can look at organizations
through so I guess what I'm trying to
say to to you Susan and thank you for
that question is in some ways as someone
working
bringing looking to bring to attention
the idea of organizations being
ecological it doesn't really feel like
my business to say how well you make
decisions with in them but as a human
being having worked in
organizations
and
um having worked with relationships and
how groups work together it feels to me
that we can choose to put that lens on
like using something like the framework
and we can as part of that focus
on um how we make decisions and for me
that always comes back to things like
consent decision
making um
to really looking more at the kind of
organizational design and
governance um but it was one thing that
I thought was very interesting in my
understand of active inference and
Daniel correct me if I'm wrong
but it's my understanding is that active
inference is doing exactly what Susan's
pointing at is understanding how
Collective behaviors Works how decisions
are made is that
right there's a lot to say there okay
certainly yes the essence of active
inference is that inference thing that's
on the inbound doing sense making with
whatever information it has whatever
modalities it's getting and then on the
outbound is making decisions based upon
whatever affordances it has and you in
response to that question you said well
viewing the organization as ecological
doesn't put a
preference on the structure and it's so
funny because we talk about preference a
lot in active inference too and
similarly active inference doesn't put a
preference on what body plan or what
algorithm or what organizational
structure one should use it's just a
descriptive understanding framework and
so AC of inform applied to organizations
it also is not opinionated as to whether
there should be 1 3 5 7 consensus this
style that style those are all
conversations to have and to be
described as
situations but it's like we're
opinionated and can express our values
and who we are to the extent that the
framework doesn't and to the extent that
the framework loads on the horror
decisions that would be us offsourcing
and reducing our
expressivity with simply a more
opinionated tool which might work well
where that's the right opinion to have
but won't work where that isn't the
opinion to have and even where it is the
right opinion to have it almost silently
robs the organization of
that of taking agency over that
structural
agency right that's that's exactly the
word that was coming up for me listening
to you agency
because for me every organization is
unique to be any any being any ant
colony any any ecosystem all of these
are unique so um It's always important
to me that any organization or the way I
see it would be like any
organization Finds Its Own
way of being an organization in that
sense right in the practical way like
how they make decisions how they govern
what their systems and structures look
like what work they do all of those
things um I've always struggled with I
you know I have so much um appreciation
and more than that like huge respect for
for for something like sociocracy or
hocy um I've worked in both I'm trained
in trained in Hy 3.0 and I think they're
incredible but and I I could never look
at an organization and say well all
organizations should be sociocratic or
all organizations should use um halacy
or in fact all organizations should use
consent or just holy consent because
that that kind
of that brush we can't brush it with
that often with those one colors like
most governance systems most
decision-making most social norms are
are very distinct and they they
they sit somewhere on a border between
like say like like centralization and
decentralization in how they do things
and how they work um um mostly consent
but sometimes consensus um doing a lot
of group work in sense making but also
individual sense making and all of those
things and I think what you're speaking
to what's interesting about um active
inference um so for me I hold ecological
organizations as almost neutral in the
sense that like an animal is an animal
we don't say they're good or bad or they
look this way you know ants act as ants
it's look understanding that an
organization is full of relationships
that
affects um and is IM mesed in mass of
other
relationships feels incredibly important
the for me the ecological organizations
framework that I authored is a very
specific tool it's like an an addition
it's kind of like if you're interested
if you've had that kind of like leap of
perspective and you now understand how
deeply relational your organization or
an organization is and you feel that
activated um that activation towards
stewardship towards now what now how can
what's some of the options how can we
look at it then the pH framework becomes
potentially very useful because it kind
of gives you this very specific way in
but the framework is so saturated with
me and my
perspectives um that I can imagine and I
hope there will be there could be many
different Frameworks about how to relate
with or be in an ecological organization
and I'm sure they would all just be as
valid um and as fascinating and as
supportive of collective decision making
awesome so on the live stream I'm I've
brought up and maximized the square
image that you've created and I'll just
read the ecological organization circles
so there are integrating more than human
encouraging Rich diversity and cohesive
disruption embodying the commons moving
closer to right relationship embedding
seasonality activating ecosystem
responsiveness and
responsibility stewarding a
self-organizing system and becoming more
relational so how did you come to this
pallet or this layout or or even
approach with so many questions in the
outside yeah that's um I love that a
question and it is so hard to answer
because really this
framework
represents all of the work that I've
ever done in a way with organizations it
reflects really what I see or have seen
as the elements that create well let's
put it this way so if if an ecological
organization
is is a is a is
a we we we're calling it a being it's
it's own being um we're understanding
the organizations of their own beings
and now we want
to activate ourselves as human beings
within those ecological
organizations those are all the elements
that I see as being the important
elements to focus on that help us become
stewards and help us become in a form
deep relationships with the organization
itself um and really when I created the
framework I didn't mean to create a
framework what I was trying to do
was reach this point in my life when I
realized that I was moving further away
from previous work that I'd done and
relating to organizations as I had done
before and was really just trying to
understand for myself what is it that I
care about what is it to me like if I
was
to if I could help instigate an
organization in certain
ways be the most radical stewards both
for the organization and for the
ecosystems and social systems it's
situated in what do I what do I see as
important and it's all of those
elements um and that's why I say that
another framework you know you could
have different Frameworks and they may
they I'm sure they'd be just as
beautiful and
important um but for me this this brings
in um really is so informed by work on
of on living systems on interbeing on um
stewardship on self-organization on um
organizational design on the way that I
see groups and um Dynamics play out um
on the kind of state of the world that
we're in right now um and the necessary
steps that or the the the steps that I
see as necessary such as the one that we
talked to before about um localizing and
and experimenting innovation in a very
kind of local controlled way so that you
get realtime feedback so I was lucky
enough to get some input on this
framework from one person in particular
who works very deeply
in in Commons and in Urban Design and
in
um um I could uh sort of building like
ecological Villages things like that and
you know they brought the attention to
the importance of real time information
and and things like that so um
you still with me Daniel we lost you Mo
oh you've gone a your picture's just
gone but yeah so
um yeah I mean I and then they became
questions through reading the work of um
uh Dr wool and his work on um
regenerative design and I realized that
um the the questions are the
most uh richest
um experience that we can have as
organizational stewards is to keep
asking questions
um
yeah thank you that's awesome I really
resonate that with asking questions what
would happen if questions were asked
from the top from the middle from the
outside from the
boundary rather than leading with direct
Ives or
commands I'll ask another question
appropriately from the chat Mills 8102
writes
question there are so many connections
to be explored Beyond ourselves as
persons and
organizations how do we prioritize and
choose which areas to explore with our
finite capacities to do
so yeah yeah that's so important it's a
question I often ask myself and I think
we have touched on that briefly when we
spoke
about um the need to somehow
find the edges of what becomes too vast
for us to hold within our awareness and
work on and what
becomes manageable
um I'm probably going to give a really
frustrating answer to that which is that
I think it where the what the priorities
are would be very very unique and
specific to um the organization to the
ecosystems and social systems that it's
situated in
um what I would find or would what I
would imagine is that Daniel you you
said something lovely earlier about like
well it's just kind of it's
just taking time to kind of almost like
sit and be and breathe and have a absorb
what's happening and it's almost like
taking space as humans to just
really sit and find some silence um and
then could be multiple ways in as
priorities um you know what's your
organization like um are there people
incredibly unhappy um are you
desperately concerned about um the
systems or structure rures that you're
you know immersed in um what's happening
in your sort of local communities what
do they care about um then there are the
kind of bigger urgencies things like um
you know the the climate pressure like
where's your relationship with that that
could be an entryway in like what's the
role that your organization might play
um to to
help support people through this or to
to make changes there's so many I think
different ways that an organization
would or could prioritize and find
entryways in um on a personal level I
think it's probably about Gathering as
much information as you can um listening
as much as you can to others like what
do other people
see um what do they think of
priorities um and then and then finding
something that really fascinates you
that's something we often forget about
too like where do you personally feel
pulled what what gives you excitement
and energy to work on or to look at and
examine and
explore um maybe you should make that a
priority I don't know I find that's a
very personal um a very
personal situation for each of us and a
very going to be very unique every
organization and and this the ecosystems
and social
systems well in active inference where
we're creating these formal models of
sentient
things it often comes up like how can
something be such a general scaffold
such that we can fill in the details and
make it an organization or an organism
and like in terms of how we think about
decision-making it often is decomposed
not to go too deep here but into two
components a pragmatic and an epistemic
and the pragmatic is about making the
world as we expect it to be like making
our organizational culture or the
narrative as we expect it to be and the
epistemic is like the mystery and the
Curiosity and the open-endedness and
there's this blend in every action or at
least in how it's chosen between
bringing the world into alignment with
the preferences of the thing and that
thing learning more and that that seems
to be a place that can be pulled back to
that can explain the activity of non-c
curious things like a metronome it just
carries out its task rhythmically right
all the way on through purely curious
things that don't have any pragmatic
Preference they just seek to explore
information and this is part of the
ecosystems of shared intelligence which
is something that people in the active
inference field talk about is like
rather than constructing
monolithic architectures bigger and
bigger models we can already think about
our ecos systems as a piece of paper
here and an old computer here and a
person here and the office cat here it's
like we're already in this space where
the causal networks flow across bodies
and networks and
computers and we Overlook that
heterogeneous reality again already at
our own Peril because it's already how
things are
[Music]
yeah I mean ABS I I can absolutely I I
can yeah I mean it's what it's so
fascinating because I I think you know
we're sort of looking at the same things
but maybe in this or our entryway into
how we're looking at it is is you know
my entry way into this is through as I
said earlier it's through my kind of
lived experience of myself and I think
um that having as someone who's had
chronic health conditions their whole
adult life you know they kind of the
impact of that has made me explore my
reality and my body and my world in a
very different way and it there's
certain things like it it it limits my
capacity it limits what I can focus on
but it also heightens things um it gives
me a very kind of perhaps visceral
experience of what it's like to walk
through the world with with a kind of
queerness that some people might not
experience so there's all these kind of
different entry ways into it and I you
know one of the things that I really
hesitated with when I brought out their
framework was what if people read this
as an answer like what if people read
this as an end goal as a like oh just
take the framework and put it on an
organization and we can just follow
these questions and that's it and I and
that would I'd find that heartbreaking
if that happened because you know but
but but at the end but we also as humans
you know I I need you to sit here and
talk to me about active inference I need
you to
hold all of your knowledge about it
because I don't have the capacity or
probably even the interest in the same
way you do to dive into it in the same
way you do and you might not have the
same interest to hold and dive into
ecological relationships or
organizations in a way that I do and I'm
not saying you don't but and I think
that's what I find
so you know sometimes I feel this
pressure it's like I don't know enough I
don't know enough I need to know more I
need to how do we make these decisions
without more information more knowing
without being more rearranged by
knowledge and and then I have to kind of
breathe and I have to go quiet and I
have to kind of remember that we are
millions of people and we're holding all
of this different information this
different knowledge and these different
entryways into something and that just
feels a miracle to me it feels so
exciting and if we can just hold all of
these things as these lowercase tees
these truths that are more
questions um I'm Cur can I ask a
question um tell me like what are the
some of the kind of living questions
maybe that you Daniel or or more
generally your community kind of lives
into well I love that I hope in comments
and in conversations everybody can give
their thought I'll I'll give a personal
anecdote I guess
yeah to to my experience with organizing
your question brought me back um more
than 10 years ago to organizing a chess
club in
undergraduate and bringing out tables to
the farmers market and playing chess
with people and myself not not being the
best chess player in the group not even
close not ever having competed in chess
but wanting to show up with the boards
and facilitate that space where people
who had years of Chess or minutes of
Chess could have fun and the question
that mystified me then and I see in a
new clothing today is some people would
walk by the
boards and it would just bring them joy
to see that
we were out there and they would just
whether or not they stopped and played
they would like it made them excited
maybe it reminded them of yeah their
passion and other people had seemingly
intense negative reactions right like
that the existence of a game was even
with with or without them playing was
was was a threat or that that that was
that somehow there their Worth or that
their their
relevance was was on the line seemingly
for chess in a way that if we had
Checkers on the table maybe it wouldn't
have seemed so
um I see it again now with as we
organize variously in kind of purely
relational communities of
care online friendships and and
relationships but also
including technical open- Source
ecosystems with science and technology
engineering math and art in all these
different areas
and how do
we how do we have an organization so
that
our the passer
by and those inside and those outside in
that boundary moment it's something that
makes people feel warm and right with
who they are not
like I should have been doing something
different in my past such that I should
have been a different person right now
just because I saw a
[Music]
chessboard that's an amazing question
and it seems to hold so many other
questions in it as well about like sense
of self and
um ah just yeah
fascinating thank you for
sharing I'll ask um one last question
from the chat sure yeah yeah please do
yeah awesome so Susan asks what are
barriers for people to begin in
exploration in other words what is scary
confusing and overwhelming full of
surprise maybe that's in reference to
the framework or maybe just in the
organizational
work yeah well let's maybe start with
the framework and we'll go backwards I
mean I can imagine that for a lot of
people it could be overwhelming just to
sit with the framework like where do we
even find entry here do we resonate with
this these areas maybe there's some we
do and some we don't maybe there's
language here we don't resonate with or
um what is a more than human being I
mean I've been asked that before you
know like that's not a terminology or
even a kind of perspective that people
that everyone holds
um um so I mean I'm I can imagine that
there might be quite a lot about the
framework and so I
that's and I I I I struggled a lot with
like how do I produce this thing and be
true to it and also not be scary and
kind of um
like do I change my language do I all of
these things and then it felt like no
all I can do is I think as any of us can
do and I maybe I'll change my feeling on
this future is all we can do is be true
to like what's within us and what we see
and bring it into the world with as much
care as possible so that the the people
that can connect with it can and the
people that don't don't I'm not that
worried about the amount of people that
won't connect with something like this
framework they'll find something else
they can connect with they'll find other
language that matters to them they'll
find different areas and and I also like
if someone took the framework and they
said oh half of this seems absolute
rubbish but I half of it kind of
resonates and I'm curious and I want to
dive into this one particular question
well great you know it's like fabulous I
think we should all follow the
breadcrumbs and interests that matter to
us um as to having an I guess it feels
like maybe slightly different question
with with the nature of ecological
organizations because in some way that
feels
more vital more urgent in some ways I I
feel like our I feel an
urgency that more people recognize that
organizations are
ecological um and that organizations are
likely causing harm and help and all of
these things but they're having impacts
and they're affecting
things um that to me feels urgent for
these times um and as bio akafi always
says when in urgent times we slow down
so or let's slow down
um but I can imagine that it might be
very hard for people
to hold the TR like what does that mean
when we start to like look at an
organization as this massive web of
constantly changing fluid relationships
that are IM mesed in other fluid
constantly changing relationships you
know you and I have been there on this
conversation it's a
tension we have to hold it's an almost
an
impossibility
um
um I don't know the answer to that
really I I mean that was why I spent so
much time working on the kind of
visualization for this talk was like how
do I it felt like an impossible question
to me how do I bring something that
feels like it's very personal and comes
from my lived experience as a human
being and how do I
somehow share that in a way that might
trigger other people to have their own
personal experience because it feels to
me important
that we don't
hold organizations as these
lifeless theories these lifeless
ideas um but I don't know how to take
everyone there or I don't know how
everyone would get there
um when when you said that organ ations
like they might be lifeless and also
like almost absent your framework or
similar approach they they are lifeless
de facto and it's like well we're living
so then we're getting bled out in the
organization because then there's some
point in which the life is being
enclosed or is drawing the energy of
something
that's um from the living to the
unliving and then the organiz is part of
a death process rather than a
regeneration process but if we can be
like in a room that is living like you
mentioned with your colleague in the
case of a physically living building but
but you also brought up other senses not
just the architecture but socially
living and so on then we would be like
Warm Bodies in a warm
room instead of like our energy always
just being
dissipated by these
cold synthetic intelligences that aren't
human and aren't
aligned right yeah interesting I I think
I would slightly challenge that in the
sense that I'm not sure they
organizations can be dead or
cold I I'm not sure they can I think our
experience of them can be and our
experien as a human interacting with
them and being a member in them can
leave us cold and feeling deadened
inside and certainly the experience I
had that brought me to self-organization
is that I felt I was like my soul was
dying within certain businesses and
organizations um but I don't think they
are I think though that how we stewarded
these
organizations in the same way like do we
we let's back yeah how we Steward them
will change how we experience them so if
a group of people I think about this the
other day like let's say a group of
people all get together and they you
know it does like let's take Amazon it
doesn't feel like there's a soul within
Amazon right it doesn't feel like the
people that came to birth and Steward
Amazon have done that with with heart
and soul and kind of connected to life
that's my experience of it does that
make Amazon the organization dead not to
me it doesn't but it's like what they've
what they've nurtured and stewarded
without being aware of it maybe or
through their
intentionality becomes a very different
experience and say an experience of an
organization that's being nurtured and
birthed through awareness and
connectivity and care and compassion and
humanity and
um and
love so that's where I'd be with
it well you took on an impossible
challenge as you said but you
took
steps and now I hope that the ecosystem
can meet you on this interface object
you've created and I guess in closing
where do
you intend to take the work or like what
will be exciting for you going
forward yeah well one thing that came
very clear to me as I was as as the
framework was coming together was um it
makes immense sense to me it comes from
kind of pulled from so many different
worlds of experience and knowledge and
information and it um it's had a great
response in the world from people that
have really connected with it I know
that it's being utilized in a couple of
different schools and Business Schools
already it's kind of wow that's amazing
um people are uh bringing it into their
organizations but and that's that's
amazing to me and also was that sense as
I was bringing it together that this
needs now some real world experience
like everything else this feels in a bit
like an infant or a or a young child
that's been kind of nurtured into the
world and now it needs real life
experience so the more that the
framework can be interacted with the
more it can be explored um on a personal
level it said the more that happens I
think the Richer it will be and and it's
it needs that um on a personal level I
have I've had a long kind of sense that
I would like to some to start a
community because of the interest it's
gathered or kind of come together draw
people in that are fascinated with
holding up this lens of ecological
organizations um and um support them by
bringing in um people from all these
different worlds that inspired it such
as interbeing and sense making and um
self-organization and all of these
things um so yeah I'm curious to see if
I'm kind of got this sense that post
Christmas I'll probably be initiating
that as a community and and I would like
to support them and I'd like to gather
information and real world real life
data from that and and I'd like to start
if I can working with organizations that
are drawn to the
framework um to to see what happens as
we over the longer term as we apply it
and utilize it like what changes about
the framework and I'm just like I'm so
be so excited if people have if anyone
listening to this or watching this has
ideas sees ways it could evolve or be
worked with like I'd love them like let
me know because you know it's had it's
it's got life to it but the more life
that can be given to it the Richer and
the more it will
grow thank you
awesome anything
else just thank you so much much for
having me it's um I I've never found or
I've always found writing easier than um
sitting in kind of something like this
but I actually really really enjoy it
and um I'm thank you so much for your
care in the in your thoughtfulness in
the questions and I've loved our
discussion and for everyone listening
thank you for sharing your thoughts and
your questions and um just if you want
to find me on LinkedIn or through my
site anyone want watching this that gets
activated and excited by it wants you
know support to enter it or anything
like please let me know I'd love
that thank you well best of luck and see
you around I hope that we can continue
to explore this I'd like that thank you
Daniel have a good day see you you too
bye